how to overcome
anxiety that's something
everybody everybody would wonder at
least at some point in their life but I
I think probably many people today it's
it's quite a quite a pressing
issue um the most um most important
thing to to
realize at first is that um well is to
stop resisting it you stop trying to get
rid of it that's the necessary necessary
steps it's um important uh it's it's
good that that people uh see anxiety as
a problem so you don't just go around
ignoring it or or trying to trying to
forget about it through engaging with
sensuality at the same time you do have
to recognize that
uh that wanting to be free from it in
the long run is not the same as uh as
trying to to to get rid of it right away
right here and now and it's that is that
pressing need impatient need of um of uh
removing it as soon as it arises or as
soon as it starts arising that's why it
makes it so uh much more
unpleasant so if you stop trying to get
rid of
it then you can you can can well you can
be able to um to see it closer to see it
for what it is and what it is is that um
it's not a it's not an acute issue or or
a or a problem that has arisen as a kind
of mistake it's really
um mirroring of a of a very basic um
very primordial existential uh
primordial existential uh
principle uh existential discrepancy if
you want to call it like that
which is that um this life of mine my
own life my own uh my own environment uh
it's not my own in a sense of uh
fundamentally things upon which my life
rests things that determine my life are
not in my
control and that's why anxiety actually
uh far from being like an acute problem
or or or some error in in your
programming it's uh it's really just um
just a revelation of the of the most
certain thing when it comes down to your
existence and that thing is it's the
your own existence is not in your
control doesn't mean that your choices
are not in your control but means that
choices are already
within that existence that you have no
say in it you have no say in the
in the fundamental aspects of your
environment you have no safe in the
circumstances that can affect your life
you can only do the best you can uh
within that limited amount of control um
but if you look at it closely
fundamentally no amount of control can
ever can ever change or upturn that
order and and truly make you the master
of your own experience of your own life
why because
fundamentally the the fact that you're
going to be subjected to elements to
change adverse change or positive
change the fact that that remains there
as something you're fundamentally and
utterly subjected
to uh that's exactly uh what anxiety uh
reveals reveals that reveals discrepancy
between your assumption of your world
and the actual nature of it and that's
the that's why anxiety is unpleasant if
you were to remove uh the uh the
discrepancy if you were to remove the
view that believes that you are the
master control of your feelings for
example um that that would basically uh
remove the unpleasant aspect of anxiety
and then anxiety would not be anxiety as
as you know it it would simply be a
recognition of the fundamental principle
of life which is it is not in your
control it cannot be fundamentally
Yours by that I mean you cannot be the
owner because if you were truly the
owner the life the feelings would obey
you you would feel only what you want to
feel you would experience only what you
want to
experience but the fact that that that
that's simply not possible you end up
living your life at at odds with a with
a very nature of it you your attitude
towards your own feelings pleasure
displeasure ual feelings is at odds with
the actual nature of those feelings they
arise on their own they manifest them
themselves to you and the problem that's
where the problem arises whereby when
Pleasant feelings manifest themselves to
you you want them and you feel fully
entitled in doing so you feel fully
entitled in going after them you feel
fully entitled in entertaining them um
building building your decisions and
choices upon them and so
on but now you have when you have a um a
disagreeable feeling arises you equally
feel fully entitled to trying to get rid
of it right away I I I must not be
feeling this I should not be feeling
this so that's what I mean in order to
like like such a kind of subtle
overwhelming yet so General experience
of of orison anxiety unpleasant anxiety
the first thing is to stop acting out of
that sense of I have a right to not want
this whatever has a reason it has a
reason on its own be this feeling or
that feeling which means
um your rights stop there so to speak
you have a right to choose like this or
to choose like that you have a right to
take responsibility for your choices but
you have no you don't have a right to
not feel this or because whatever it's
being felt it's felt on the basis of
this life that subjected to
feelings so that's why it's it's really
the anxiety is really not about freeing
yourself from the unpleasant feeling
it's freeing yourself from The View that
you yourself impose upon the very
present experience that you have at a
time that then results in this
discrepancy so you and and you can't get
rid of a view whatever A View is
overnight it won't happen so so you
can't uh just suddenly shift your view
and be free from everything that bothers
you view is it's it's really like a like
a like a habit like a habit of a certain
way of perceiving things so now you need
to reprogram the way you perceive things
and you reprogram it when you start
following the principles for
reprogramming not just uh when you want
to act out of it when things are only
unpleasant now I want to do it then when
anxiety is gone you forget about it and
you pretend like it was never there and
your life is fine there's no such thing
as fine life as in there is no such
thing as life free from anxiety or
suffering there is no such thing as as life that
there is no such thing as as life that
doesn't require taking up
responsibility that doesn't require
work so it's really not that's not
optional what is optional is how you're
going to go about it are you going to be
trying to mask the fact that anxiety
reveals you the most fundamental nature
of your existence that you're not in
your control that your life is not in
your control like mask it pretend it's
not there distract yourself with with
Central Pleasures or are you going to
start accepting responsibility for it
and start looking at
it and
um if it's sometimes you might feel
overwhelming and
unpleasant um and that's uh pretty much
because most of the habits are still
concerned about running away from it and
not accepting it so it's going to take
time to be able to accept it and once
you accept it then you as I said then
you realize well the unpleasant aspect
of anxiety it's not necessary anxiety in
itself as a revelation of of that
discrepancy that your life is the way
it's lived that is absolutely fine
that's just how it is you remove the
discrepancy you remove that displeasure
of that
anxiety so if
a it's if a person ex it would be good
starting point to to sort of um stop
expecting an override solution stop
resisting trying to get rid of it that's
probably the most
important and if you you know when you
have thoughts oh how great things would
be without
this without this anxiety you can use
that as a motivation to to make the
effort to understand anxiety but don't
use that as a justification to want to
get rid of
it because the Notions you have of oh
how great it would be of being anxiety
free are are really um
fantasy like if if the life was in your
control if the life was the way you
think it
is anxiety would be
inconceivable but the fact that it isn't
the fact that it has Arison the fact
that you're experiencing it means now
you have an option you're either going
to pretend that that's a mistake or
you're going to start looking into your
own attitude towards your own life and
realize that that's the bit that needs
changing because as I said anxiety is a
symptom it's not a
problem it reveals the discrepancy that
you yourself generate and maintain with
your attitude towards your own
existence it's not the problem of your
existence existence itself is not a
problem the problem arises when there is
a discrepancy when there is a certain
disparity and and that's what normal is
normal life is the life based upon that
disparity contradiction
and that's why normal life requires that
constant sort of Engagement and
maintenance that's why people are afraid
of solitude that's why people are
superstitious all these little like fear
of solitude for example just starts
pointing you back towards that which
you're running away from with your daily
distractions and actions and projects
and meanings and so on when you're alone
you're just left with your own thoughts
and what's going to show itself first
well first going to be bordom then it's
going to be dread and anxiety because
your whole life is about covering it up
and that needs constant kind of floating
constant swimming on the surface
Superstition same people develop magical
beliefs to mask that that little crack
in their existence where anxiety shows
its head
through but again if existence were
perfect if existence is the way you
would think it is none of these things
would be
conceivable anxiety displeasure for that
matter would be absolutely inconceivable
you could not think
it why because you would be the master
controller and things would be
corresponding to that Mastery your
choices your feelings your intentions
which means there would be no
discrepancy to be felt as displeasure so
it's it's really comes down to um down
to changing your view in regard to your
own existence upgrading it because it is an
upgrade once the once once you become
aware of the problem once you become
aware of the
anxiety
uh means you become aware obviously
unwillingly of the fundamental aspect of
your own
life an aspect that's very unpleasant
not in itself but it's unpleasant
because of your own assumptions in
regard to your own life that OD with it
stop trying to get rid of the anxiety is
the first step the second step is you
have to start looking it at looking at
it as a symptom not as a problem not as
something I must deal with it but
something that has an underlying cause
that's being revealed to me through that
anxiety and that underlying cause um is
that is the very nature of your life of
your feelings of things you're subjected
to which is at odd with what you think
those things are or what you feel feel
those things should
be so that's that's why that like
naturally that view that assumption
carries already a sense of
entitlement um but but for that
assumption you responsible simply
because you don't dwell on that
nature of that underlying nature of that
of that experience so you don't you
don't dwell enough on the fact that
you're not in your control you don't
dwell enough on the fact that feelings
arise on their own
and you're subjected to them I mean you
can you can act out of them you can try
to cover them up but fundamentally you
can never appro your liability to
feel good bad or neutral you just can't
so your efforts are only
secondary the amount of input you can
you can make it's only
relative it cannot fundamentally upturn
that picture but see not thinking about
these things feeling entitled to not think
things feeling entitled to not think
about these things and then feeling even
further uh entitlement towards
sensuality and pleasures and craving and
ambition in in in in life and trying to
get your desires
fulfilled that's how you proliferate
that very discrepancy between how things
actually are and how you think they
should be and that's exactly that's
exactly where where anxiety is so
removal of your expectation how things
should be uh learning how to accept the
way things ah and that's something as I
said you not do it in a second you have
to you have to keep drilling it you have
to keep training yourself in regard to
it because you really are not just
dealing with one particular problem
you're you're re reprogramming the
entire attitude towards your own
existence that you have and
reprogramming takes time takes
repetition um until you undo the the
wrong programming habits habits of
trying to get rid of the unpleasant
feelings as soon as they manifested
habits of trying to to to run away from
the unpleasant feelings as soon as
they're manifested but that's also another thing
manifested but that's also another thing
you can think about why is unpleasant
feeling be anxiety or anything else why
is it my problem the anxiety
arises it's felt unpleasantly why is
that an issue why do I immediately I
must get rid of this why I don't I mean
I'm still fully aware and fully
responsible for my actions so I don't
need to choose or decide to do anything
on account of it why I cannot just be
with it something worth dwelling on and
it something worth dwelling on and
equally when Pleasant feelings when
enticing sort of perceptions manifest
themselves and you want that pleasure
ask yourself why why do I have to follow
this desire why I cannot just remain um
equanimous towards
it again it doesn't neither desire for
sensuality nor anxiety and and and and
unpleasant feeling neither of those
things makes you act you are the one who
chooses to act upon
it yeah they can exert different
pressure and that different pressure
means different amount of discrepancy
and that depends on where your views are
at the more you feel entitled to
sensuality the more pressure is going to
exhibit on
you same the more entitled you feel to
be free from any unpleasant feeling the
more frightening anxiety will be
but again doesn't doesn't matter how
much fear or how much pressure toward
Central pleasure and desire is
manifested you are the one fundamentally
and ultimately who decides to act or not
out of it so that's where your
responsibility is so you realize I don't
have to act out of this I don't have to
do anything I don't have to do anything
on account of the Oris anxiety I could
just patiently allow it to endure but
then the the the mind will be I must get
rid of it I must get rid of it well I'll
endure that thought as well I'll endure
those states of Mind why because
fundamentally as I said anxiety is not
the issue that accidentally ER
erroneously um arose on account of your
perfect existence anxiety is an issue
that reveals to you that existence in
its nature is
imperfect but the imperfection it's not
in existence it's in your attitude
toward your own existence
so that's why that's why really uh
anxiety it's it's almost like an
existential Awakening because most people everybody
Awakening because most people everybody
experien anxiety there's absolutely
that's not optional and that's that's
the first thing is going to become
apparent if you start accepting it as a
symptom of your resistance not as an
issue you'll see that everybody
everybody subjected to it but the
difference is that most people are still
able to maintain that that that thin
layer of ignorance ignorance very frail
layer of ignorance upon
it so they they can pretend it's not
there but it is it's always there it
always has been always will be for as
long as the view to what your existence
is at odds with the existence so it's
always there but some people are still
able to keep distracting themselves from
it but that doesn't mean they're dealing
with it it actually it makes things
worse the more you're distracting
yourself from it the more of that
discrepancy The Habit that results in
the discrepancy is being
reinforced so if you spend your whole
life running away from anxiety
ultimately catches up with you when
death comes how do you think it's going
to feel if little other the public
speaking of other or other things cause
you anxiety how do you think when your
life starts to shut down how how that's
going to feel when little threats to
your existence secondary threats to your
existence make you make you anxious
imagine when the that threat is actually
being realized and you are dying for
whatever reason doesn't matter what
bring what what what brings death on the
point is that's what anxiety is that's
what anxiety shows you that your life
can end at any given time and you have
no say in that yet you live your life as
if you have a say in that your health
can end in any given time yet you're
fully intoxicated with the fact that
you're not ill now and you think you're
never going to get ill same with with
youth strength uh and age that's why
those three Divine Messengers that the
Buddha himself was talking about
sickness aging and death um are the um
like Messengers they're the symptoms of
the problem they're not the problem so
you realize this is inevitable so I
better tailor my views my attitude
towards my existence to match this so
that there is no discrepancy discrepancy
affecting me destroying me and and and
really really making me suffer when it
comes so trying to trying to not get rid of it
so trying to trying to not get rid of it
accepting it and then um developing an
attitude towards your own anxiety uh as
a symptom of an underlying
problem not an issue in
itself and uh in order to approve the
issue that anxiety is symptom of you
have to start well you have to start
modifying your own life and your own
views to it and if you feel like oh it's
too much work look at all these happy
people around me that's your own mind
sort of Playing Tricks on you in a sense
of um in a way it's a lazy thinking I
don't want to do work look how these
people are happy I just want to be like
that I just want this to go away that is
wishful thinking and you can carry on
wishing that and the more you wish it
the more you'll be subjected to to that
discrepancy or you could take up
responsibility for it and and realize no
this is something worth worth addressing
something worth dealing because it's not
something you need to do every time if
you truly properly address it and deal
with it that's it there is no
discrepancy to be felt anymore that's a
true Freedom there is no pressure of of
sense desires that you can or cannot
fulfill there is no fear of what if this
happened what if that happened there are
still those thoughts what if this happen
what if this happen but those thoughts
are now not causing any discrepancy
because you have no expectations
certainly not assumed fixed expectations
as to oh this must happen or this should
happen so in that Cas in that sense anxiety is
so in that Cas in that sense anxiety is
still there but now you are not there
with it anymore you you you you went
beyond it the reason it bothers you is
because it threatens to overwhelm you
but it threatens to overwhelm you
because you're too weak in regard to it
and you're too weak in regard to it
because you never want to take
responsibility for developing strength
towards it but if you do so and you make that
it but if you do so and you make that
effort of being able to allow it to
endure not carelessly acting out of a
habit trying to get rid of it not
carelessly trying to distract yourself
from it through sensuality and desire
then you'll see it coming and going yet
your mind composure will remain
unchanged and that is a true Freedom
when you are not liable to the pressure
of your own feelings whenever they arise
whatever whatever they might be as well
so when there is pleasure you're not
trying to get more of it automatically
when there's pain you're not trying to
get rid of it
automatically and when there's neither
pleasure nor pain you're not distracted
automatically so the feeling arise and
endure but the Mind State the the the
the composure of your mind uh remains
completely unaffected by that this
should also answer answer the question
whether there is a there is a some
technique meditation technique you can
do uh in order to overcome
anxiety um that question as it should be
well clearer from this by now would be
coming from the that that view that I
should be getting rid of this that I
should not feel anxiety in the first
place and um
so so so once you once you stop having
such expectations you realize there is
no a prescription method that you can do
that will then make you that prevent you
from feeling this it will be like a
prescription method that will make you
that will prevent you from existing
while you're existing there is no such
thing um which is why again we go back to the
um which is why again we go back to the
same the most important thing you can do
in regard to the experience of
anxiety is like swallow the the hard
pale of uh of Truth in a sense of that
you realize it really shows you what
realize it really shows you what
existence is
about it's not something that can be
ignored and then you can pretend that it
was never there and continue your life
merily and
ignorantly so so if you if you're able
to accept that as a truth that's already
a massive step forward in order to be
able to not be affected by anxiety you
can't get rid of it in the same sense
you can't get rid of your own existence
you can only grow out of that anxiety
whereby when it arises you are not
affected by
it and the only way you'll stop being
affected by it is if you stop running
away from it which keeps giving it
power so a symptom
that tells you that reveals the
underlying nature of your existence well
it's not what you want to be it's not
what you assume to
be so if you're willing to accept it as
such that's all you already have to it's
already like less than half of a problem
the main problem is people still
maintaining the prior or the Notions PRI
prior to the anxiety PRI well not prior
to anxiety you're always subject to
anxiety prior to their anxiety becoming
self-aware and then you think that was
the norm before that but it isn't as I
said if that were truly the norm anxiety
would have not Arisen in the first place
because if you were truly the master
controller of your feelings of your
environment of your
life you would feel only what you want
to feel and the Buddha himself spoke
about it many times says which feeling
is yours as in which feeling you think
you control because they keep
control because they keep
changing but if you were truly the
controller you would only feel what you
want to
feel and you can apply the same
principle towards your own thoughts if
you were truly the controller of your
thoughts you would only think what you
want to think but no thoughts manifest
themselves they present themselves to
you and then you make choices and
decisions and think further based upon
that but fundamentally they have Arisen
on their own that's why they did
fundamental ultimate respon
responsibility for your actions no
amount of thoughts arising on their own
no amount of feelings pressuring you on
their own none of that can make you act
only you choosing to act makes you act
and that's what you're fully responsible
for and there is no excuse for that
because none of the feelings none of the
thoughts none of the even the intentions
that present themselves none of them
automatically result in this action or
that oh I've done this because of that
no you done this because you chose that
to be the reason for doing
this and and that's that's simply
there's no alternative to
this so that's why that acceptance of
what you're subjected to in terms of
feeling in terms of thoughts terms of
the environment Acceptance in a sense
not okay I I don't I won't do anything
about it Acceptance in a sense I must
not trying to get rid of this but
instead I have to look where the real
problem is which is in the discrepancy
that I create in regard to things that
I'm subjected to
so yeah I mean if if uh if certain type
of environment it's causing you
overwhelming anxiety sure turnone it down a bit don't
anxiety sure turnone it down a bit don't
expose yourself to it but not for the
sake of Sheltering yourself from anxiety
just for the sake of giving giving
yourself a bit of a break so that you
can regain strength to deal with
it and you you don't deal with it by a
go straight into what makes you anxious
no you as I said you deal with it by
changing upgrading reprogramming your
views about that thing that causes you
anxiety or about life in general your
expectations your entitlements your
assumptions if you get that to
match the actual nature of existence the
actual nature of your life then there
will be no discrepency so the the the
the less disparity between the two
the less uh liability to anxiet the less
less amount of symptoms will be
showing and that's why that's what I
mean it's it's a gradual work gradual
effort gradual Acceptance in a way and
gradual reprogramming and you can only only do
reprogramming and you can only only do
so not based out of a out of a out of a
mechanical kind of sets of observances
and rules and I do this and I do this no
you can only do so by reflecting upon it
so you can can only do so by accepting
the fearful aspect of it bit by bit but
you realize that's the work that needs
to be done not that's the work that I
must get rid
of it's done when it doesn't affect you
it's not done when it's just not
there because as I said anxiety mirrrors
the nature of
existence which means in a way that
mirror is always there it's just whether
you're going to suffer on account of it
or not